בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody. Today's דף daf is קי"ד. kuf yud
daled. We pick up at the bottom of קי"ג עמוד ב'. kuf
yud gimmel amud bais. We're dealing with the מצוות mitzvos related to
not seizing, entering into the house and seizing collateral, returning collateral of
a poor person on a regular basis. And then the גמרא Gemara
introduces this important issue, which is going to be for a lot
of today's דף, daf, which is מסדרין לבעל חוב. mesadrim l'baal chov.
Arrange things or תוספות Tosafos or רש"י Rashi suggest, leave things over
for
the debtor, that when you come, presumably not to take collateral, but
presumably when you come to collect your debt when the time comes,
do you have to leave the person anything or can you just
take all of his property? And the מסדרין לבעל חוב mesadrim l'baal
chov no means we have to leave him some basic necessities to
live off of, and we learn that from ערכין Erchin because by
a person who makes this ערך, erech, a specific type of a
vow to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash where the תורה Torah sets
fixed amounts, the תורה Torah also says that if he doesn't have
enough money, the כהן kohen assesses him and determines how much he
can afford, and then that fixes how much he's obligated. So that
actually changes the degree of his debt, but from there we learn
that you assess how much can be afforded and what does that
mean? Like you mean you have to determine a certain base amount
the person to live off of. And does that become then the
basis for saying that when you collect a debt, you leave over
certain amount, which is not, let's make it clear, not the same
because it doesn't mean like if the guy owes like bankruptcy court,
you can declare bankruptcy and you pay half and you're done, you're
free of your debt. That's not what we're talking about here. You
owe ten thousand dollars, we assess that we'll leave you some clothes
and your house and some basic stuff and we'll be able to
collect five thousand dollars. Okay, you still owe the other five thousand
dollars. It's just that we're not gonna take that basic stuff and
leave you houseless and without any clothes and without any food. So
it's not the same as bankruptcy.
It's just that
we're not gonna debtor's prison, what?
More like the idea of garnishing wages that you get.
Oh, okay. That's a way, right. Right, right, right. That's a way
of thinking about it, right. Okay, so anyway, that's what we said.
So the גמרא Gemara just has a problem or wants to prove
against that from Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel because Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
in the משנה Mishnah said that this thing here, when it says
when you take something like his, you take his clothes or whatever
you take and it's an עני, oni, you return it on an
ongoing basis. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says that after thirty days you
can actually sell it and liquidate it to pay off your debt.
So it seems like you don't leave the guy anything. So the
גמרא Gemara says, well, maybe what you're doing for Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel is you're selling an expensive cloak and leaving him a more
simple one. But the גמרא Gemara says, well that doesn't work because
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel together with other תנאים Tannaim in different contexts
have this idea of כל ישראל בני מלכים הן. kol Yisrael bnei
melachim hein. And therefore it would not be, it would not justify,
if you say that you have to leave something some basic amounts,
well if the guy's been going on around until now with a
silver embroidered cloak, then for him, that's his, he's entitled to say
that's my basic need of clothing. So within that approach of כל
ישראל בני מלכים, kol Yisrael bnei melachim, you would not be able,
like again, if he had ten cars maybe you could take away
nine, but if his remaining car is a Rolls Royce, you can't
say just go ahead and manage with a Ford. Okay, so that's,
so then, so within Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, it sounds like אין
מסדרין לבעל חוב ein mesadrim l'baal chov because if you were מסדר,
mesader, you would not be able to sell off these things even
to buy something cheaper. So let's just, let's just finish that idea
in the גמרא Gemara because we didn't finish the whole that whole
issue of כל ישראל בני מלכים הן. kol Yisrael bnei melachim hein.
So let's just look here at the bottom of קי"ג עמוד ב'
kuf yud gimmel amud bais
which where it's a real nice expression of it not in Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel but in Rabbi Yishmael and Rabbi Akiva. So it
is seven lines from the bottom, line starts with the word מלכים
הן melachim hein and it says the following: Rabbi Yishmael Rabbi Akiva.
Now who where did Rabbi Yishmael and Rabbi Akiva express this idea?
דתניא de-tanya we learn in a ברייתא: Baita: היה נושין בו אלף
זוז, haya noshin bo elef zuz, so somebody had creditors who had
a thousand dollar זוז zuz debt against him. ולבש איצטלא בת מאה
מנה, velavash istila bas me'ah maneh, and he was wearing a gorgeous
Armani suit worth at least a thousand dollars. מפשיטין אותו ממנו mafshitin
oso mimenu ומלבישין אותו איצטלא הראויה לו. u-malbishin oso istila ha-re'uya lo.
So there you go, you take it away from him and you
replace it with a nice more basic garment. I mean, the הראויה
לו re'uya lo presumably means this is what is הראויה לו re'uya
lo if you owe a thousand dollars and you don't have anything
else to
pay. דתניא משמיה דרבי ישמעאל ודתניא משמיה דרבי עקיבא. de-tanyei mishumei d'Rabbi
Yishmael ve-tanyei mishumei d'Rabbi Akiva. But we have ברייתות Baitas in the
name of Rabbi Yishmael and a different one in the name of
Rabbi Akiva that reject this and say: כל ישראל ראויין לאותה איצטלא.
kol Yisrael re'uyin l'osa istila. No,
all Jews are, this gorgeous garment is fit for any normal Jew.
Okay, if this is what the guy is wearing, he's entitled to
it if we have this deep sense of like dignity and royalty
to us that we are entitled that it's considered to be fit
for us. So therefore for them, even
if you were to say מסדרין, mesadrin, you would not be able
to sell something fancy for something more basic. I mean like this
comes up nowadays in bankruptcy court, why the guy has this huge
mansion, ten million dollars, is he entitled to save it, to keep
it, because that's my home? Or do you say no, you gotta
sell it and live in something more basic? Okay. Okay so now
the גמרא Gemara continues. ולמי דסלקא דעתן מעיקרא דיהבי ליה מאי דחזי
ליה ומזבנינן מאי דלא חזי ליה U'lemai desalka daitchan meikara d'yaivleih mai
dechazi lei umezabninan mai delo chazi lei now
according to the גמרא Gemara says what we thought initially that if
we're going to be מסדר לבעל חוב mesader l'ba'al chov we leave
him what he what's appropriate for him and we sell what is
in excess, okay, בשלמא כר
וכסת bishlama kar u'chesset meaning and even the same type of an
object. If it's a fancy one we sell it and we buy
him a more basic one, if we take that type of an
approach, not בני מלכים, bnei melachim, so we're going to sell the
fancy stuff and leave you more basic. So בשלמא כר וכסת bishlama
kar u'chesset I get a pillow and a blanket, חזי ליה דביני
ביני, chazi lei d'beini beini, you could understand a nice fancy what
is it five hundred thread four hundred thread down blanket and selling
it for you know polyester. Okay I get it, there's a difference.
אלא מחרשה Ella makhresha but now the question is what does מחרשה
makhresha mean? I'm going to translate it now as a plow. If
we're dealing with a plow, למאי חזיא? le'mai chazya? So what you
know how do you get a what's the difference between an expensive
and an inexpensive? They're all the same, they're a plow. What what
is this difference that you would sell it for? So the גמרא
Gemara says אמר רבא בר רבא Amar Rava bar Rava right,
אמר רבא בר רבא מחרשה
דכספא.
Amar Rava
bar Rava makhresha d'chaspa.
No
let's say this guy's got a silver plow. Now that's a little
absurd like you know you might have all the money in the
world to throw away but what the heck are you doing you
have a silver plow? So תוספות Tosafot actually says and there's another
problem because in the context of the משנה, Mishna, the משנה Mishna
was talking about returning it on a daily basis right based on
this פסוק, pasuk, right, כי היא כסותה לבדה היא שמלתו לעורו במה
ישכב והיה כי יצעק אלי ושמעתי Ki hi k'suto levada hi simlato
le'oro bameh yishkav vehaya ki yitzak elai veshamati and תוספות Tosafot says
and this is really interesting because it's not clear from the פסוקים
pesukim and it's not clear from the גמרא Gemara that this מצוה
mitzvah to daily return it if he's an עני ani only applies
תוספות Tosafot says to things that are fundamentally about like the the
person's direct clothing and care of his body, okay, that כי היא
כסותה לבדה היא שמלתו לעורו ki hi k'suto levada hi simlato le'oro
speaks about lying down in the clothes, you know, returning a pillow
at night, returning nightclothes, dayclothes. Those are the things that the גמרא
Gemara refers to, okay, so תוספות Tosafot actually says which is which
is very interesting so if you take his plow which is his
means of livelihood now the plow gets to this other question of
ריחיים ורכב rechain varachev what's considered כלים שעושה אוכל נפש? keilim she'oseh
ochel nefesh? It's another interesting debate. Some ראשונים Rishonim say this would
include a plow because you use a plow for making food. Others,
תוספות Tosafot also reads it in a more limited way and says
it means only vessels that are used directly directly with food like
a mixing bowl, a grinder, a mill, that's ריחיים ורכב rechain varachev
you're directly if you're plowing ground it's not. So you can take
away a person's means of livelihood and it would not fall into
this פסוק pasuk and it wouldn't fall into this מצוה mitzvah and
you wouldn't have to give it back to him on a daily
basis. So that's like a little shocking, right? Yeah others disagree. So
anyway according to תוספות Tosafot though you wouldn't have to return a
plow on a daily basis. So therefore תוספות Tosafot says what is
a מחרשה? makhresha? תוספות Tosafot says a מחרשה makhresha is he brings
some evidence that it's like a type of a comb like a
body comb. He brings another גמרא Gemara but you could understand it,
right? Do you see what a plow looks like? Right it's got
like those types of you know prongs, right? So anyway so תוספות
Tosafot says so therefore it's a what the עמוד א amud aleph
it's a something that you use for the body and therefore it
has to be returned on a daily basis and then you could
also imagine having a silver comb and having a plastic comb and
that's what the גמרא Gemara would say would be the case of
what you would do if it would be if it would be
מסדר לבעל חוב mesader l'ba'al chov yeah.
Are we always thinking that the plow is worth all the debt
is or is it just part of the debt?
Might be either.
Because if it was only part maybe then if he takes his
means of livelihood away he's gonna have less of a chance of
getting
I understand
that's for the creditor to figure out you know but that doesn't
necessarily mean that he's not legally entitled to do so, right? Yeah.
And
the old plow just has one oh really?
The old one does have one oh well so much for that.
Maybe two. All right so right all right so I don't know
but nevertheless תוספות Tosafot
is תוספות Tosafot on the משנה? Mishna?
No it's on the עמוד א amud aleph it's דיבור המתחיל dibur
hamaschil והא מחרשה
ביומו.
v'ha
makhresha beyomo.
Yeah I'm just trying to understand it. I mean you know the
guy also can always sell himself into slavery right if he can't
pay back the debt.
Yeah but we
עבד עברי eved Ivri right what
we don't have like evidence of עבד עברי eved Ivri I mean
you can choose to sell yourself as an עבד עברי eved Ivri
maybe if you'll
sell your right if you
stolen it right if you stolen
it and then you couldn't but then it says right okay well
all gone in a mansion go somewhere but if he owes a
debt we wouldn't make him do that. Right right.
אמר רבא בר רבא Amar Rava bar Rava now okay we did
that. Now מתיב ליה רב חנא Masiv lei Rav Chana now now
moving on מתיב ליה רב חנא masiv lei Rav Chana ולימא ליה
לאו עלי רמיא u'leima lei lav alai ramyia
it's not my responsibility to support you. Now what is this what
what's bothering him which phenomenon of what we're discussing is he bothered
with? מסדרין לבעל חוב? mesadrin l'ba'al chov? You're not exactly supporting a
guy when you're מסדר לבעל חוב mesader l'ba'al chov you're just leaving
him some basic necessities. So תוספות Tosafot says the challenge is the
idea that going back to this you you know return his garment
on a daily basis and according to these ideas of בני מלכים
bnei melachim you would even return his garment If it was this
beautiful Armani suit. So it's like, why is, why do I have
that responsibility? Like why would the תורה, Torah, if he's rich, you
don't have to return the stuff on a daily basis. If he's
poor you do. So he's poor and I have to return it,
but so why is the תורה Torah asking me to return this
beautiful expensive object if, you know, like it does like where's the
logic in this? I get the idea that בני מלכים, Bnei Melachim,
but still, you know, why do I have this מצוה mitzvah to
return it on a daily basis? So he says, אמר ליה אביי,
Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said, אברא עליך רמי, Ivra, aleika
rami, no, in truth it is your responsibility to take care of
this guy. שמשום שנאמר, She'mishum she'ne'emar, ולך תהיה צדקה, V'lacha tihiyeh tzedakah,
it'll be considered as righteousness when you return this garment on a
daily basis. So even if you feel that's on this, on this
פסוק, pasuk, so even if you feel it's a crazy expensive garment
and I'm sorry the guy is poor but I should be able
to sell it, no, the תורה Torah says that's what you do
to maintain his dignity and yes, it is, you know, that is
your responsibility. Okay. איבעיא להו. Iba'ya lehu. Now, after having discussed מסדרין
לבעל חוב Mesadrin l'Baal Chov and having a ברייתא baraita that essentially
says it, we're going to report a new version of this discussion
or parallel version of this discussion. They raised the following question: מהו
שיסדרו בבעל חוב? Mahu she'yesadru b'baal chov? Can, do you make arrangements
for the debtor and leave him over some basic stuff when you're
coming to collect the debt? So מגמר ממיכה מיכה מערכין? M'gamur micha
micha m'erchin? Does it, you know, do you make a גזירה שווה
gezerah shavah because by ערכין Erchin it says וכי ימוך אחיך? v'chi
yamuach achicha? I'm sorry, by a loan it says וכי ימוך אחיך,
v'chi yamuach achicha, if your brother becomes poor and you know, you
have to support him, and then it says if you lend him
money, and by ערכין Erchin it says ואם מך הוא מערכך. v'im
mach hu m'erkecha. If he is so poor that he cannot pay
the donation he made to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So since
by ערכין Erchin we have this idea of מסדרין Mesadrin and the
same word is used by a poor borrower, debtor, maybe we say
that we apply the same law. אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, or not.
תא שמע, Ta shema, come hear, דשלח רבין באגרתא, d'shlach Rabin b'igarta,
רבין Rabin sent in a letter: דבר זה שאלתי לכל רבותי. Davar
zeh she'alti l'chol rabosai. I asked all of my Rebbes this question:
do we make this גזירה שווה? gezerah shavah?
ולא אמרו לי דבר. V'lo amru li davar. They never, they weren't
able to give him the answer. ברם, Beram, however, כך הייתה שאלה.
kach haisa she'eilah. The following question did arise, did arise in the
בית מדרש, Beis Medrash, and we can infer from the assumption of
this question an answer to our question. Here was the issue that
did come up in the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. האומר הרי עלי
מנה לבדק הבית. Ha'omer, harei alai maneh l'bedek habayis. Somebody is not
the case of ערכין. Erchin. ערכין Erchin is you say ערך, Erech,
you know, Michael, ערך Erech this person עלי, alai, okay? And therefore
it says, well, is he male or female? What's the age? Let's
look it up on the chart. This is how much you owe.
It was a very specific set way of donating to the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. The other thing is a guy just says, right,
האומר הרי עלי, Ha'omer, harei alai, I'm going to donate a thousand
dollars to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. That's not ערכין. Erchin. That's
just a נדר neder to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So would
you apply the idea of מסדרין Mesadrin to other cases of הקדש
hekdesh that are not ערכין? Erchin? Okay, that's a similar question, right?
The guy can't pay his donation to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
but it's not ערכין. Erchin.
האומר הרי עלי מנה לבדק הבית. Ha'omer, harei alai maneh l'bedek habayis.
I'm going to give a thousand dollars to the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. מהו שיסדרו? Mahu she'yesadru? And he doesn't have that money, would
we leave over something? Now again, it's not like ערכין Erchin because
ערכין Erchin is you redetermine the amount of the debt. But at
least here the question is, do we at least, do we strip
him of all his property to pay his donation to the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash or do we leave him some basic amount and
he'll pay the rest when he gets around to paying the rest?
Okay, so מהו שיסדרו? Mahu she'yesadru? Do we do this in this
case? רבי יעקב משמיה דבר פדא Rabbi Yaakov mishmeih d'Bar Pada ורבי
ירמיה משמיה דאילפי v'Rabbi Yirmiyah mishmeih d'Ilfi אמרי, amri, קל וחומר מבעל
חוב. kal v'chomer m'baal chov. We can make a קל וחומר kal
v'chomer from a debtor. ומה בעל חוב שמחזירין, U'mah baal chov she'machazirin,
אין מסדרין. ein mesadrin. By a debtor, you have an obligation to
return the collateral, right, if he's poor. And nevertheless אין מסדרין. ein
mesadrin. So what they're taking as their assumption is that you do
not, you're not מסדר לבעל חוב. mesader l'baal chov. You don't leave
him over a basic amount. So if that's true by a בעל
חוב, baal chov, that even though you return collateral, you do not
show him the sort of accommodation of מסדרין, mesadrin, even though you
have this obligation of
מחזיר, machazir, הקדש hekdesh where הקדש hekdesh has no obligation to return
collateral that it's taken how we know that we'll find out in
a minute but if הקדש hekdesh has no obligation to return collateral
that is taken from people that owe הקדש hekdesh money, so אינו
דין שאין מסדרין? eino din she'ein mesadrin? So how much more so
would they not have a responsibility to leave over the guy some
basic amount? So that's their argument that by הקדש hekdesh that isn't
ערכין, erchin, אין מסדרין. ein mesadrin. But what we see from the
implicit assumption of that argument is that אין מסדרין לבעל חוב. ein
mesadrin l'baal chov. Now let's finish this discussion about הקדש. hekdesh.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: רבי יוחנן אמר לא. Rabbi
Yochanan amar lo. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan disagreed, not about the assumption
but about the הקדש hekdesh point. נדר בערכך כתיב. Neder b'erkecha kesiv.
It says a vow with the ערך. erech. So it connects ערכין
Erchin with other types of vows. מה ערכין מסדרין, Ma erchin mesadrin,
the same way other vows you make this arrangement, אף הקדש מסדרין,
af hekdesh mesadrin, by הקדש hekdesh as well. Okay, so there's a
debate whether you apply the idea of ערכין Erchin to other cases
of הקדש hekdesh about מסדרין, mesadrin, but everybody agrees with the assumption
of אין מסדרין לבעל חוב. ein mesadrin l'baal chov. So the גמרא
Gemara says ואידך, v'idach,
now what would the other אמוראים Amoraim do with this word of
נדר בערכך neder be'erkecha since they don't link it? ההוא לנידון בכבודו
הוא דאתא. Hahu l'nidon b'khvodo hu d'ata.
That's to tell you to apply the law of judging with someone's
weight or significance. I'll explain in a minute what it means. מה
ערכין נידון בכבודו, ma Erchin nidon b'khvodo,
the same way by ערכין Erchin you judge based on the weight
of the thing that was being valued, the significance of it, so
אף הקדש נידון בכבודו... af hekdesh nidon b'khvodo... I lost my line,
my place... אף הקדש נידון בכבודו, af hekdesh nidon b'khvodo, similarly by
הקדש. hekdesh. Now what does this mean you judge something based on
its significance? So this is if somebody says, if somebody doesn't say
ערך פלוני עלי, erech ploni alai, but it says ערך erech of
the guy's heart עלי, alai, or ערך erech of the guy's lungs,
or the guy's liver, or the guy's head. So since all of
those are things that the body needs to live, then it's like
I said the ערך erech of the person on me. But if
I said ערך erech of the guy's arm, then I'm not obligated,
'cause the arm is not the whole person. So it seems like
I have to catch... so that's the principle of נידון בכבודו. nidon
b'khvodo. So similarly if I say דמי פלוני עלי, d'mei ploni alai,
not ערך, erech, but the amount, which means the amount it would
sell in a marketplace, or let's say I said דמי שור... d'mei
shor... slave market... דמי שור עלי, d'mei shor alai, I pay the
amount of that ox that would go at in the marketplace. Let's
say I said דמי רגל שור עלי. d'mei regel shor alai. Okay,
there's a market for the leg of an ox, if it's slaughtered
kosher I assume. Okay, let's say I said דמי d'mei the heart
of the שור shor עלי, alai, then you would assess it based
on the whole value of the ox. So that's the principle of
נידון בכבודו. nidon b'khvodo. So we learn that הלכה, halacha, but we
do not learn this הלכה halacha of מסדרין לבעל חוב. misadrin l'baal
chov. So there's a debate whether you apply מסדרין misadrin
from the ערכין Erchin case to other הקדש hekdesh cases, but everybody
agrees אין מסדרין לבעל חוב. ein misadrin l'baal chov. Rabbi...
yes,
so the word כבודו kvodo here means the whole entity?
Yeah, רש"י Rashi says it means the significance of the thing. So
if something represents the whole body, so כבודו kvodo means no, it
means the significance of the limb that is being assessed.
Wait, but I thought he just said...
right, the significance of the heart is that it represents the whole
body.
Whole thing, like if I said פלוני כבודו, ploni kvodo, it's like
the whole thing.
Maybe, maybe. I don't know if I would say that parallel,
but for someone who's let's say publicly in there's an appeal in
the שול, shul, and values says oh I'm in for whatever it
is and he can't do it, is there any like application of
that?
Well, I mean we're working just to move from one case of
הקדש hekdesh to another. Then to go from a הקדש hekdesh case
to other types of צדקה tzedakah would be like another movement. But
if you're asking like are we מסדרין לצדקה, misadrin l'tzedakah, that's an
interesting question. Yeah, I'd have to see that. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Okay, והשתא... v'hashta... now that we've assessed that
the assumption that אין מסדרין לבעל חוב, ein misadrin l'baal chov, but
we are maybe we are מסדר להקדש, mesader l'hekdesh, maybe maybe not,
that's a question. Now the גמרא Gemara turns it around. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. ויסדרו בבעל חוב קל וחומר מערכין.
v'yisadru b'baal chov kal v'chomer me'Erchin. I don't get it, let's make
a קל וחומר kal v'chomer from ערכין Erchin to say you should
do מסדרין בבעל חוב. misadrin b'baal chov. ומה ערכין שאין מחזירין מסדרין,
u'mah Erchin she'ein machzirin misadrin, we just got through saying that הקדש
hekdesh including ערכין Erchin never has to return collateral, so הקדש hekdesh
that doesn't return collateral nevertheless affords the accommodation of מסדרין. misadrin. בעל
חוב שמחזירין, baal chov she'machzirin, by in a normal case of two
lay people that you would return the collateral to the debtor, אינו
דין שמסדרין, eino din she'misadrin, you certainly should afford this accommodation of
מסדרין. misadrin. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אמר קרא, amar kra,
for that we have a פסוק. pasuk. ואם מך הוא
מערכך, V'im makh hu me'erkecha, if he, the person who made the
vow, can't afford the vow, then you make this arrangement. הוא ולא
בעל חוב. Hu v'lo baal chov. It's limited to vow or maybe
the world of הקדש, hekdesh, but this accommodation does not extend beyond
it. So now we're learning from a פסוק pasuk to not extend
this accommodation beyond this case.
The קל וחומר kal v'chomer therefore would have been good except for
the פסוק.
pasuk. Right, it was a good argument. Exactly. Okay, ואידך, v'idach, now
what would the other one say? Meaning the one that would actually
say that maybe you would go
to... ואידך v'idach means the one that would
say מסדרין לבעל חוב? misadrin l'baal chov? No, 'cause that's assumed it's
not true. But the one that would say מסדרין בהקדש. misadrin b'hekdesh.
Isn't הוא hu a limiting word? Maybe it should limit it just
to just to a case of ערכין. Erchin. So the response to
say הוא hu is not so limiting would be to say the
following. האי עד שיהא במכותו מתחילתו ועד סופו. Hai ad sheyehei b'makhuto
mitchilato v'ad sofo. ואם מך הוא מערכך, V'im makh hu me'erkecha,
if he remains poor is when you make this reassessment. But if
let's say he was rich when he vowed and poor when it
came time to do the assessment, or poor when he vowed and
rich when it came time to do the assessment, you do not
make this accommodation. The accommodation for ערך erech is only when he
was consistently poor. Okay, moving on. Now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. ויחזירו בהקדש קל וחומר מבעל חוב. v'yachziru b'hekdesh kal v'chomer m'baal
chov.
Now that we've asserted this difference between מסדרין, misadrin, let's go back
and argue that הקדש hekdesh should have an accommodation... A responsibility to
return collateral, make a קל וחומר kal v'chomer from a debtor: ומה
בעל חוב שאין מסדרין מחזירין, U'ma baal chov she'ein mesadrim machzirin, a
בעל חוב baal chov that you don't make this accommodation of מסדרין,
mesadrim, you don't leave him over basic amount, nevertheless you return collateral,
הקדש שמסדרין, hekdesh she'mesadrin, by הקדש hekdesh which makes the accommodation by
a person who vowed and leaves over basic amount, אינו דין שמחזירין,
eino din she'machzirin, how much more so should we assume that they
should have to return collateral? That's a pretty good argument. אמר
קרא, Amar krah, the verse comes and teaches: ושכב בששלמתו וברכך, V'shachav
b'salmato u'beiracheka,
he will lie down in your cloak and give you a blessing
when you return his object. יצא הקדש שאין צריך ברכה. Yatza hekdesh
she'ein tzarich berachah.
So you, you need a ברכה berachah from this guy, that's why
you have to return. הקדש Hekdesh can do without your ברכות. berachahs.
There, you know, God, God gives them enough of a ברכה berachah
or God doesn't need your ברכה, berachah, depending if you think it's
הקדש hekdesh is just things from God, you know, but either way
they don't need your ברכות. berachahs. So this is such a beautiful
theological next line of the גמרא. Gemara. ולא, V'lo, since when does
God not need our ברכות? berachahs? והכתיב ואכלת ושבעת וברכת את ה'
אלקיך. Ve'haketiv V'achalta v'savata u'beirachta et Hashem elokecha. God needs our ברכות.
berachahs. Okay. So, על הטוב שנתן לך. al hatov she'natan lach. So
it's actually interesting, I was just when I was in Israel, I
was I met with, you know,
Meir Lichtenstein. I go back many many years. We were חברותות chavruses
many years ago. So we're just getting together and שמוזינג, schmoozing, he
was telling me about the work he's doing for his dissertation about
ברכות ראשונות berachas rishonas in the גמרא Gemara and how the ideas
evolved over time, etc. So he actually said that originally the idea
of ברכה berachah before you eat was not blessing God. It was
blessing the food. Like you give a ברכה, berachah, like so the
food should like, you know, increase. Like you, you know, so you're
not thanking God for the food, you're blessing the food. Anyway, but
here, but the blessing afterwards where there's no food to bless, you're
blessing God for what you ate. That's ואכלת ושבעת וברכת את ה'
אלקיך. V'achalta v'savata u'beirachta et Hashem elokecha. Anyway, so yeah, maybe God
does need our ברכות. berachahs. So you can have a lot of
fun with that theologically. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so, so
maybe הקדש hekdesh has to return the object. So the הקדש hekdesh
should get your ברכה. berachah. Oh, thank you הקדש, hekdesh, you should
be blessed for this wonderful thing of returning my object. Okay, you
know. So what does it... what?
We make the ערך, erech, we make the assessment for the, for
the guy, for הקדש. hekdesh. If he can't afford, we leave him
something. But he does take something, they don't give it back.
Exactly. That's what we're saying. אין מחזירין, Ein machzirin, they don't have,
הקדש hekdesh does not have to return collateral. And the question is
why not? So the first argument is הקדש hekdesh doesn't need your
ברכה. berachah. So I mean now, it doesn't mean you only return
collateral to get the ברכה, berachah, but it means from the construct
of the פסוק, pasuk, it's clear, it's clear that הקדש hekdesh isn't
being referred to, it's clear that only lay people are being referred
to because it's talking about people that want a, that need a
ברכה, berachah, you know. That's the implicit context that we're talking about
lay people and not הקדש. hekdesh. So the גמרא Gemara says since
when? הקדש Hekdesh also could be in that context. So the גמרא
Gemara says, okay, הקדש hekdesh also could get your ברכה. berachah. So
the גמרא Gemara says, ולא, V'lo,
okay, אלא אמר קרא, ela amar krah, okay, another part of the
פסוק. pasuk. It says: ולך תהיה צדקה Ul'cha tihyeh tzedakah לפני ה'
אלקיך. lifnei Hashem elokecha.
So, מי שצריך צדקה. mi she'tzarich tzedakah. יצא הקדש שאין צריך צדקה.
Yatza hekdesh she'ein tzarich tzedakah. So הקדש hekdesh might want your ברכות,
berachahs, but they don't need, they don't need צדקה. tzedakah. Now it's
an interesting question how is the גמרא Gemara reading the word צדקה
tzedakah here. Is it reading the word צדקה tzedakah in the rabbinic
sense which means like alms, you know, charity. I don't, I don't
like using the word charity which is a very Christian word. But
anyway, alms however sounds like less respectful of the, I don't know.
Anyway. But does it what?
Alms sounds more Christian.
I was going to say.
Really? Alms sounds more Christian? Okay. But charity, charity is a whole
Christian idea that's the opposite of
צדקה, tzedakah, because צדקה tzedakah is an idea of צדק, tzedek, of
like a righteousness, whereas charity is this idea that you don't deserve
it and I'm giving it to you even though you don't... Anyway,
alright, we're not going to get into that whole discussion right now.
Anyway, are we understanding if, if the גמרא Gemara presumably understood is
reading the word צדקה tzedakah here in the rabbinic sense, I'll just
call it charity of charity, okay, then you understand. הקדש Hekdesh doesn't
need your charity. Okay. God doesn't need your charity. ברכה, Berachah, oh,
blessed, whatever, but he doesn't need your charity. If צדקה tzedakah means
righteousness, a good deed, considered as a good deed, then it doesn't,
since when does that not an appropriate thing to say about הקדש?
hekdesh? Right, we also say: God is צדיק, tzaddik, צידוק הדין, tzidduk
hadin, right? There's a, we always sort of recognize the צדקות tzidkus
of God's actions. But anyway, presumably it's treating it here as charity.
So הקדש hekdesh is not in this פסוק, pasuk, this פסוק pasuk
only refers to lay people. So only lay people have responsibility to
return objects, not הקדש. hekdesh. So the irony is הקדש hekdesh doesn't
return
collateral, but it's מסדרין, mesadrin, it makes arrangements for you not to
strip you bare if you owe money. Whereas a בעל חוב baal
chov is the opposite. Lay people is the opposite is that you
have to return the object, the collateral, but you can essentially strip
the guy bare when it's time to collect the loan. Rabbi Dov,
you had a question.
Well, just on
the ברכות ראשונות... berachas rishonas...
Can we not go in there right now? Okay, thank you.
Alright, so, alright, yeah,
what's the point of collateral if you're not going to get it
back?
So the גמרא Gemara is going to get to that question. Okay,
what do you mean if you're not going to, even if you're
not going to keep it? to the creditor are not going to
keep it? No. What are you asking one more time?
So collateral is I'm giving you something to ensure that I'll pay
you back and then I'll get the collateral.
Right. Oh no, no.
מחזירין Machzirin means you return it on a daily basis. Of course
if you pay your loan, you get it back. But the idea
of this mitzvah to constantly be giving it back, that doesn't apply
to הקדש. Hekdesh. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, I'm just going to have to interrupt because I can't pass
over an opportunity for telling a good joke, which is not exactly
relevant, but the idea of whether הקדש Hekdesh needs your ברכה Bracha
or not, right now it's like it reminds me of the story,
which is, you know, somebody comes to this רב Rav and says,
"רבי, Rebbe, רבי, Rebbe, give me your ברכה." Bracha. So he pushes
him off, he says whatever, he says, you know, "Yeah, no ברכה
Bracha is whatever." And then so the שמש Shamash says to him,
he says, "Why didn't you give the guy the ברכה? Bracha? I
mean, you know, the גמרא Gemara says that אל תהי ברכת הדיוט
קלה בעיניך, al tehi birchas hedyot kala b'einecha, it says אפילו ברכת
הדיוט, afilu birchas hedyot, אפילו ברכת הדיוט אל תהי קלה בעיניך." afilu
birchas hedyot al tehi kala b'einecha. He says, "Okay, you give him
the
ברכה. Bracha. You want a ברכת הדיוט." birchas hedyot. Anyway, fine. Moving
on. All
right. So, I don't know why I had to tell that joke.
Okay. Moving on. So, anyway, the
גמרא Gemara now we have the following story. יצא הקדש שאין צריך
צדקה. Yatza Hekdesh she'ein tzarich tzedakah.
So now presumably this whole גמרא, Gemara, as opposed to the previous
one, a very dominant message that אין מסדרין לבעל חוב. ein mesadrin
le-ba'al hov. Now we're going to tell a story. אשכחיה רבה בר
אבוה לאליהו בדקאי בבית הקברות של עובדי כוכבים, Ashkechiya Rabbah bar Abbuha
l'Eliyahu bedekai be-veis ha-kevaros shel ovdei kochavim,
that you weren't seeing that coming. So okay, we're going to see
that. So anyway, רבה בר אבוה Rabbah bar Abbuha found אליהו הנביא
Eliyahu HaNavi who was hanging around in a cemetery, in a non-Jewish
cemetery. אמר ליה מהו שיסדרו בבעל חוב? Amar lei mahu she-yesadru b'ba'al
hov?
And he said to him, "What's the הלכה? Halacha? Do you make
arrangements for a בעל חוב?" ba'al hov?
And he can do that. All right, all right.
אמר ליה גמר מיכה מיכה מערכין. Amar lei gemar micha micha m'erchin.
We learn a גזירה שוה gezeira shava from ערכין. Erchin. גבי ערכין
כתיב ואם מך הוא מערכך, Gabi Erchin kesiv v'im mach hu m'erkecha,
if he's too poor to afford it. וגבי בעל חוב כתיב וכי
ימוך אחיך. V'gabi ba'al hov kesiv v'chi yamuch achicha. And therefore presumably
that's the basis for saying that מסדרין לבעל חוב mesadrin le-ba'al hov
against the גמרא Gemara we said earlier. Okay, now he asks him
another question. מניין לערום שלא יתרום? Minyan l'arum shelo yitrom? How do
we know if somebody is naked, they can't take תרומה? Terumah? Now
רש"י Rashi intends to point out the problem here is actually you
can take תרומה Terumah if you're naked, but you can't make the
ברכה Bracha that precedes taking תרומה. Terumah. So why did he ask
it about this? Why didn't he just ask in general how do
you know you can't say ברכות Brachos when you're naked? Because there's
a משנה Mishnah that says that you can't be תורם torem when
you're naked because of the ברכה. Bracha. So he's asking like what
is the basis for that משנה? Mishnah? But it's really about the
ברכה, Bracha, not about the תרומה. Terumah. Oh, is that right? דכתיב,
De-kesiv, because the so he answers the verse says ולא יראה בך
ערות דבר ושב מאחריך, velo yireh becha ervas davar v'shav me'acharecha,
so that sense that nakedness and God's presence don't go together. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so now that we answered those questions of what's
the הלכה Halachic basis for those things, he said to him, לאו
כהן הוא מר? Lav Kohen hu Mar? Aren't you אליהו Eliyahu a
כהן? Kohen? מאי טעמא קאי מר בבית הקברות? Mai ta'ama kai Mar
be-veis ha-kevaros? What are you doing hanging out in the cemetery? So
רש"י Rashi points out, right, he's a. רש"י Rashi points out that
there are
different opinions, you know, some say אליהו Eliyahu was פנחס, Pinchas, which
makes him a כהן, Kohen, others disagree. So, you know, so he
was saying, so presumably he was assuming that אליהו Eliyahu was פנחס
Pinchas or was a כהן. Kohen. So I don't know why אליהו
Eliyahu just didn't say, "I פסק pasken like the other people who
say I'm not a כהן." Kohen. Anyway, but no. So okay, so
אמר ליה amar lei I have a more naive question.
Yes, this is not a Jewish cemetery, right? You don't need a
טומאה? Tumah?
Well, that's what we're going to find out. ולאו כהן הוא מר?
V'lav Kohen hu Mar? Aren't you a כהן? Kohen? מאי טעמא קאי
מר בבית הקברות? Mai ta'ama kai Mar be-veis ha-kevaros? Why are you
in a cemetery? אמר ליה לא מתני מר טהרות? Amar lei lo
masni Mar Taharos? Have you never learned טהרות? Taharos? דתניא De-tanya we
taught in a ברייתא, Beraisa, רבי שמעון בן יוחאי אומר, Rabbi Shimon
bar Yochai omer, קבריהם של עובדי כוכבים אין מטמאין, kivrehem shel ovdei
kochavim ein metam'in,
the graves of non-Jews don't cause טומאה, Tumah, שנאמר ואתן צאני צאן
מרעיתי אדם אתם, she-ne'emar v'aten tzoni tzon mar'isi adam atem, you are
my flock, the flock of my shepherding,
you are people. אתם קרויים אדם ואין עובדי כוכבים קרויים אדם. Atem
keruyim adam v'ein ovdei kochavim keruyim adam. You are called אדם, Adam,
you people are you, not עובדי כוכבים. ovdei kochavim. Now there's a
whole problem because obviously there are many other גמרות Gemaras that you
that say האדם Ha-Adam is coming to include non-Jews. And there's a
lot of תוספות Tosafos in there that try to figure out whether
the גמרא Gemara assumes האדם Ha-Adam is דוקא davka meant to include
non-Jews or exclude non-Jews. תוספות Tosafos makes distinctions between אדם Adam and
האדם. Ha-Adam. Maybe it's a different תנאים. Tannaim. רבי שמעון בן יוחאי
Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai maybe excludes non-Jews, others don't. But obviously it's
very harsh because it's other than just the specific question about are
they included in do they cause טומאה, Tumah, it's a claim that
they not they don't fully deserve the designation of human, of אדם.
Adam. Now you could say it's just a hermeneutic point, but even
if the גמרא Gemara just meant it as a hermeneutic point, you
know, clearly it it creates a certain attitude about seeing like, you
know, a basic sense of humanity.
Right, exactly. So anyway, it's a very harsh גמרא Gemara and it's
obviously a much larger discussion, but there are counter גמרות Gemaras and
there are, you know, questions about the term אדם. Adam. But nevertheless,
that's his position. So anyway, so they don't cause טומאה. Tumah. By
the way, I should say that that does not mean that if
you touch a dead corpse of a non-Jew it doesn't cause טומאה.
Tumah. Technical הלכה Halachic question here is whether it causes טומאת אהל,
tumas ohel, whether if you're not touching it but you're under the
same roof or if you're over the grave and therefore you're over
the. you know, you're directly over them or directly below them without
touching them would it cause טומאה. tumah. So this is very הלכה
למעשה halacha l'maaseh for כהנים Kohanim about going into hospitals, not only
going into hospitals. I mean we'll read תוספות Tosafos in a minute
about what the הלכה halacha is. The general assumption is that the
הלכה halacha is is that they don't cause טומאה באהל tumah b'ohel
the bodies of non-Jews, but some are חושש choshesh for the possibility
that they do. So for example I have my brother-in-law is a
כהן, Kohen, so my nephews who are a כהן, Kohen, they won't
go into like a museum because like the Metropolitan maybe they probably
wouldn't go anyway because they're whatever from Lakewood but anyway, but they
won't go in because of the mummies. So because of the mummies.
So there are dead non-Jews in there and they're under the same
roof. Anyway, so there you go.
There are mummies in MoMA.
Yeah, but they go to the Museum of Modern Art.
Oh, MoMA they can go. Right, that's true. I said Metropolitan, I
said MoMA. Anyway, moving on. Okay, moving on. Right, I'll mention that
to them. I'm sure that'll be their next, I'm sure it'll be
this Sunday they'll be going. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, shush. So that's
why I'm able to be here. אתם קרוים אדם. Atem keruyim Adam.
אמר ליה, Amar lei,
so he said to him, why aren't you, you never learned this
ברייתא? braisa? So אמר ליה, Amar lei, so who was this that
was talking here? רבה בר אבוה, Rabbah bar Avuha, somebody? So he
said back to him, אמר ליה, Amar lei, בארבע לא מצינא, b'arbah
lo masina, בשיתא מצינא. b'shisa masina. He says I can't even master
the four basic סדרים sedarim of ש"ס Shas that are הלכה למעשה.
halacha l'maaseh. What are the four that are הלכה למעשה? halacha l'maaseh?
מועד, Moed, נשים, Nashim, נזיקין, Nezikin, and קדשים. Kodashim. Now I would
have said קדשים Kodashim because of חולין, Chullin, but רש"י Rashi says
it's all about שחיטה shechitah and טריפות tereifos and whatever, but רש"י
Rashi also says קדשים Kodashim because if you learn קדשים Kodashim it's
like you're bringing קרבנות, korbanos, so therefore there's an importance about focusing
on it בזמן הזה. b'zman hazeh. But טהרות Taharos
and זרעים Zeraim are so irrelevant, I you know, those aren't the
bottom of my priority list, of course it's not טהרות Taharos isn't
irrelevant because you've got כהונה kehunah issues, but anyway, and you got
נדה niddah issues, but anyway, those are on the bottom of my
priority list. The four that are at the top of my priority
list I haven't even mastered those. How do you think I should
know all six? So now we're talking about a very you know
major אמורא, Amora, what does he mean he hasn't mastered it? So
he said to him, אמר ליה, Amar lei, ואמאי, vamai, why have
you not mastered this? ואמר ליה, V'amar lei, so he said to
him, דדחיק לי מילתא, d'dichek li milsa, so I I have a
very hard time making a living. I'm I'm very poor and I
therefore I I don't have I don't have enough time because I
have to make a living. I don't have, you know, I have
to work to put food on the table. דברי ואיילי לגן עדן.
Dabri v'ayeilei l'Gan Eden. He took him and he brought him into
גן עדן.
Gan Eden. דברי Dabri means took him?
Yeah. What? ארמית. Aramaic. אמר ליה, Amar lei, right, right, he led
him. אמר ליה, Amar lei, פשוט גלימך, pashut glimach,
take off your cloak. ספי שקול מהני טרפי. Safi shkole mei-hani tarfei.
Go pluck and you know and collect these some of the leaves
from the trees of גן עדן. Gan Eden. You'll be able to
sell them, they'll make you rich, we'll find out why. Okay.
He said that the case for having the cloak? Talk about him
getting more.
Right, right, so thanks. I want to talk about the parallels. I
haven't thought about that one, so hold onto that thought. Okay, ספא
שקל, safa shakal, so he like he you know he he picked,
he collected these leaves, and he was taking them out in his
cloak. כי הוה נפיק, Ki hava nafik, as he was stepping out
of גן עדן, Gan Eden, so by the way I don't think
this sort of means like עולם הבא, Olam Haba, like he didn't
take him up to heaven. He took him where גן עדן Gan
Eden is on this earth, you know, there's still גן עדן Gan
Eden somewhere on this earth, we just don't know where it is.
Okay. And he was poaching from גן עדן. Gan Eden. כי הוה
נפיק, Ki hava nafik,
when he was going out, שמע דקאמר, shama d'ka'amar, he heard somebody
saying, מן קאכיל לעלמיה, man ka'achil l'almei, who is the person that
is eating, eating up their עולם הבא Olam Haba in this world?
Taking their reward of עולם הבא Olam Haba in this world, כרבה
בר אבוה? k'Rabbah bar Avuha? Who is doing this like, you know,
who else would do something like this רבה בר אבוה Rabbah bar
Avuha just did to try to take from their עולם הבא Olam
Haba for their reward in this world? You know, my wife grew
up in a very sort of פרום frum community and this mentality
of like taking away from your עולם הבא, Olam Haba, like if
we're going somewhere in Midtown and we like find a perfect parking
space, she's like, ugh, like I can't take it, if I'm going
to use up all my עולם הבא. Olam Haba. Anyway,
so anyway, so who is it that is taking from their taking,
you know, away from their עולם הבא Olam Haba in this world?
So he heard this. So נפץ, nafatz, he scattered, שדינו, shadino, he
threw them back. ואפילו הכי, V'afillu hachi, אייתי לגלימיה, ayisi l'glimei, it
he had been carrying them in his cloak, and סחית גלימא ריחא,
sachit glima reicha, and his cloak had absorbed some of the aroma
of these leaves. So זבניה, zavnei, he sold the cloak, דתריסר אלפי
דינרי, d'treisar alfei dinarei, for twelve thousand דינרי. dinarei. So now he's
got money to sit and learn. Except the end of the story
is, פלגינהו לחתנוותיה, palginu l'chasansanei, he distributed it to his sons-in-law. Meaning,
so he didn't actually maybe he didn't want to eat his עולם
הבא, Olam Haba, he didn't want to use up his עולם הבא,
Olam Haba, but now of course he's not it's still not going
to be able to, you know, to go ahead and sit and
learn more. Now this is a bizarre fascinating story which is like
was a lot of fun, that was a fun break. What about,
you know, and presumably it's only brought in because of the proof.
of מסא דבי דביתהו, massa d'vei d'veiteihu, but it's interesting to note
some interesting parallels here with earlier discussion. First of all, what were
the two things he was asking? He was asking about מסא דבי
דביתהו massa d'vei d'veiteihu and about being naked, okay, which basically reflect
the reality that he's
poor and the whole discussion here is, do you strip the guy
naked, do you leave him with nothing, what do you do, how
do you, so that's reflecting his current reality. Okay, and then he
goes into גן עדן Gan Eden and there's almost this idea of,
it's almost like you're not supposed to go in to the guy's
house and take the thing, and if you take it, you're supposed
to return it, right? So he enters into גן עדן Gan Eden
which you're normally not allowed, he takes something, he returns it, right?
Now what happens when you return it? ולך תהיה צדקה, u'lecha tihyeh
tzedakah, right? וברכך. u'verachecha.
So even though he returned it, he came away with a blessing
from the encounter, right? So there's very nice sort of like parallels
that are going on here, right? What?
The גלימא, glima, yeah.
Right. So he took this cloak, right, and in a way also
there's that
replacing, you took like instead of this big fancy one, you return
it with a more basic one, right? So there's like certain parallels
here.
What would אליהו הנביא Eliyahu Hanavi be thinking then, because he's going
to be eating his עולם הבא? Olam HaBa? Right. What would אליהו
הנביא Eliyahu Hanavi want to?
I don't know. Anyway, but it's really, I think it's very interesting
to think about the parallels of the previous story. Now, in terms
of הלכה, halacha, there's a very important תוספות Tosafot in terms of
two ways. Number one, how do we פסקן pasken מסדרין mesadrin or
אין מסדרין לבעל חוב? ein mesadrin l'ba'al chov? So the סוגיות sugyot
were back and forth, but the last סוגיא, sugya, אליהו Eliyahu at
least seems to say מסדרין לבעל חוב. mesadrin l'ba'al chov. Okay, and
he learns it from מיכה מיכה, micha-micha, so if you take a
look at תוספות Tosafot on קפיד עמוד א, kuf yud dalet amud
aleph, right? מהו שיסדרו בבעל חוב, mahu she'yesadru b'ba'al chov, he says
פסקן רבנו תם בספר הישר pasken Rabbeinu Tam b'Sefer HaYashar דאין מסדרין
בבעל חוב. d'ein mesadrin b'ba'al chov. We פסקן pasken like the earlier
סוגיא, sugya, אין מסדרין. ein mesadrin. דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל דמתניתין מסיק
לעיל דסבר דאין מסדרין בבעל חוב. d'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel d'matnitin masik
l'ail d'savar d'ein mesadrin b'ba'al chov. The whole earlier discussion was אין
מסדרין. ein mesadrin. And how about the אליהו הנביא? Eliyahu Hanavi? So
he has a different גרסא girsa with the אליהו הנביא. Eliyahu Hanavi.
The question with אליהו הנביא Eliyahu Hanavi wasn't מהו שיסדרו בבעל חוב,
mahu she'yesadru b'ba'al chov, do you do it? And he quotes a
פסוק, pasuk, it was מנין שמסדרין לבעל חוב, minayin she'mesadrin l'ba'al chov,
which means for those who say that you're מסדרין, mesadrin, what is
the הלכה halachic basis of it? Which is still a weak read,
but nevertheless תוספות Tosafot argues that מסדרין בבעל חוב, mesadrin b'ba'al chov,
אין מסדרין בבעל חוב. ein mesadrin b'ba'al chov. Okay, and then he
says now if you take a look on the next עמוד amud
of תוספות, Tosafot, he has another point. I'm sorry, the bottom of
קפיד עמוד א, kuf yud dalet amud aleph, let's just start there.
ורבנן דמתניתין, ve'rabbanan d'matnitin, the last few four words of the line
on the bottom קפיד עמוד א, kuf yud dalet amud aleph, נמי
מצי סברי דאין מסדרין. nami matu savri d'ein mesadrin. The Rabbis of
the משנה Mishnah who say that you return the cloak on a
regular basis and you're constantly returning it, they might still agree that
אין מסדרין, ein mesadrin, that you strip the guy naked. Now what
is it? Are you returning the cloak or are you taking all
of his property? So תוספות Tosafot here makes the important distinction I
made for you yesterday between the arrangements you make when you're dealing
at the collateral stage and when it's finally come time to pay.
You can make accommodations when I'm taking collateral, I'm still hoping to
get my loan paid up and I'm going to return it and
I'm not going to take all your property away when I'm taking
collateral. But if now it's time to pay up, it's already a
month in arrears and you still haven't paid and I have to
get my loan paid, then I'm not going to show any רחמנות.
rachmanut. Okay, so he says ומיירי בבא ליטול בתורת משכון. u'mairi b'vo
litol b'torat mashkon. When you're dealing, when you're taking it as a
משכון, mashkon, רבנן סברי שמחזירין לו כל ימי חייו. Rabbanan savri she'machzirin
lo kol yemei chayav. You get, will have to return this cloak,
there's no limit, as long as you're in the משכון mashkon realm,
return it on a daily basis, leave him over stuff and so
on, make sure that he has clothes etc. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
סבר עד שלשים יומא ומכרה. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel savar ad shloshim
yoma u'machra. That's when you're in the משכון mashkon mode. אבל היכי
דנטל בתורת גביה, aval deichei d'natal b'torat gviyah, but when it's finally
time to collect and you want your loan paid, יכול למכרו מיד
ולא ישדר כלל. yachul l'machro miyad v'lo yeshader klal. I don't have
to even replace a nice cloak with a lesser nice one, I
can take all your property, אין מסדרין, ein mesadrin, I don't have
to leave you with anything. Okay, so that's an important distinction about
whether we're talking about the משכון mashkon period or the paying up
of the loan.
This was done before the time was due, right? As a משכון.
mashkon.
Well, right, or you're allowing it to be extended. It's after it's
due, but you're not yet demanding for it to be paid up.
Okay, then by the way תוספות Tosafot gets into another whole discussion
about how do we פסקן pasken about to prove that the whole
debate with אליהו Eliyahu doesn't prove that מסדרין לבעל חוב, mesadrin l'ba'al
chov, he says because after all again אליהו Eliyahu says קברי עובדי
כוכבים kivrei ovdei kochavim are not מטמאי, mitamei, and תוספות Tosafot says
the real הלכה halacha is that they are מטמאי, mitamei, and he
tries to prove that קברי עובדי kivrei ovdei are מטמאי. mitamei. So
that's an important question for כהנים kohanim flying over cemeteries, hospitals, those
thing in general we assume קברי עובדי כוכבים kivrei ovdei kochavim are
not מטמאי, mitamei, but by תוספות Tosafot trying to claim that, it's
his way of saying what אליהו Eliyahu said is not the הלכה.
halacha. Okay, it wasn't the הלכה halacha by the קברי עובדי כוכבים
kivrei ovdei kochavim and it wasn't the הלכה halacha by מסדרין לבעל
חוב. mesadrin l'ba'al chov. The הלכה halacha is אין מסדרין לבעל חוב.
ein mesadrin l'ba'al chov. So you can read תוספות, Tosafot, he was
just saying he was being דוחה docheh him whatever, anyway you say
teach me... I understand, in general since when does אליהו פסקן? Eliyahu
pasken? Anyway, very important תוספות Tosafot about this
issue, about מסדרין לבעל חוב mesader l'baal hov and what's the bottom
line הלכה halacha is and the difference between when you're coming to
collect or when you're taking a משכון. mashkon. In that context, I'll
read you a רמב"ם. Rambam. The רמב"ם Rambam in פרק ג' מהלכות
מלווה ולווה perek gimmel mehilchot malveh v'loveh says the following. He
says: כשיתבע המלווה חובתו, kesheyitba hamalveh hovato, this is פרק א' הלכה
ד' perek alef halacha daled in מלווה ולווה, malveh v'loveh, when it
comes time to collect the loan, אף על פי שהוא עשיר והלווה
דחוק וטרוד במזונות, af al pi shehu ashir vehaloveh dachuk vetarud bimezonot,
you know, you're a millionaire, this guy's barely putting food on the
table, אין מרחמין בדין. ein merahamin badin. Okay? Now that's a really
harsh statement after all of this being מחזיר את העבוט mahzir et
ha'avot and לא תבוא אל ביתו. lo tavo el beito. So this
is the contrast. That's at a certain period, but at the end
of the day when it comes time to get paid, you're entitled
to have your loan paid off. אלא גובין לו חובו עד פרוטה
אחרונה, ela govin lo chovo ad pruta achrona, you could collect up
to the last penny of the debt, מכל המטלטלין שימצא לו. mikol
hamitaltelin sheyimtza lo. Okay, from any of the מטלטלין. mitaltelin. אם לא
הספיקו מטלטלין גובין המקרקעין im lo hispiku mitaltelin govin hamikarke'in etc., etc.,
etc. אחר כך מסדרין. achar kach mesadrin. Now, at the end of
it, the רמב"ם Rambam does say: אין בעל חוב גובה לא מכסות
אשתו ובניו של לווה ולא מבגדים צבועים ein baal hov goveh lo
michsut ishto ubanav shel loveh v'lo mibegadim tzvu'im etc. and
he does have all these issues about you do leave him over
some stuff, okay? מסדרין לבעל חוב. mesader l'baal hov. He פוסק paskens
against תוספות. Tosafot. מסדרין לבעל חוב כדרך שמסדרין בערכין. mesader l'baal hov
kederech shemesadrin be'erchin. אומרין הבה כל המטלטלין. omrin havei kol hamitaltelin. Get
all the מטלטלין mitaltelin and so what does he mean you can
collect all the מטלטלין mitaltelin and he מסדר. mesader. So here's what
he says: אומרין ללווה הבה כל המטלטלין שיש לך. omrin laloveh havei
kol hamitaltelin sheyesh lach. לא תניח אפילו מחט אחת. lo taniah afilu
machat achat. Bring all of your property, don't even leave over one
pin. We want to see a full inventory of everything you have.
ונותנין לו מן הכל מזון שלושים יום וכסות שנים עשר חודש. venotnin
lo min hakol mazon shloshim yom uchesus shneim asar chodesh. And then
we assess, okay, we're going to leave—now that we know the full
inventory, we'll give you a basic amount and the בעל חוב baal
hov is going to take the rest. So at the same time
of saying אין מרחמין, ein merahamin, there is really a little רחמנות
rachmanus about the מסדרין לבעל חוב. mesader l'baal hov. Okay? But anyway,
the רמב"ם Rambam פוסק paskens מסדרין mesadrin and תוספות Tosafot פוסק paskens
אין מסדרין. ein mesadrin. Yes?
Can you give him in payments? We take
all the money and then we return?
Oh, no, no. It means like you give him—you have a whole
inventory, like, right, and then, right, and then now that you have
essentially, you know, you know, I—it's—it's a little like, you know, it's
a little feeling like
stripped naked, but you have to—that's sort of where the אין מרחמין
ein merahamin comes. It's not like fundamentally I'm not entitled. Like, fundamentally
you have to show me a full inventory and to the last
penny of everything you have. I need to know how many pairs
of shoes you've got in your closet. I need to know how
many pairs of underwear you have. I need a full—I'm serious, that's
the idea. A full inventory then I'll decide how much to allot
you because of מסדרין לבעל חוב, mesader l'baal hov, right? So it's
a really shifted mentality. But anyway, תוספות Tosafot goes so far to
say אין מסדרין. ein mesadrin. Yes?
In a situation where the lender was not allowed to charge interest,
you have to have something that's going to entice people to lend
money, right?
That's a good point. I mean, there's so many things that are
stacked against the lender here, right? I mean, he doesn't know if
he'll ever get it paid off or whatever, so that when it
does come time to pay that he should have this, you know,
right, is a good point. Absolutely. Okay, so let's now continue the
גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. ואם איש
עני הוא לא תשכב בעבוטו. v'im ish ani hu lo tishkav ba'avoto.
If he's poor, don't go to sleep with his—the collateral, that's this
idea of returning it. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan.
הא עשיר שכיב. ha ashir shachiv. But if he's rich, you can
lie down with his collateral. So the גמרא Gemara thinks it means
you can actually sleep in his clothes. So מאי קאמר? mai ka'amar?
What does that mean? Like as רש"י Rashi says, why should he
be allowed to use his clothes to sleep in? You know, רש"י
Rashi says it would be a type of ריבית. ribbis. Okay? אמר
רב ששת הכי קאמר. amar Rav Sheshet hachi ka'amar. ואם איש עני
הוא לא תשכב ועבוטו אצלך. v'im ish ani hu lo tishkav va'avoto
etzlacha. Don't go to bed and you still haven't returned the collateral.
Doesn't literally mean don't be sleeping in his clothes. הא עשיר שכיב
ועבוטו אצלך. ha ashir shachiv va'avoto etzlacha. But if the guy is
rich, so the—the—the debtor,
so שכיב ועבוטו אצלך. shachiv va'avoto etzlacha. You don't have to return
it. So while this פסוק pasuk לא תבוא אל ביתו לעבוט עבוטו,
lo tavo el beito la'avot avoto, don't enter into his house doesn't
matter rich or poor, and לא יחבול ריחיים ורכב lo yahavol rehayim
varechev doesn't matter rich or poor, this מצוה mitzvah of returning the
collateral on a daily basis, that is only if he's poor. Okay?
So תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. המלווה את חברו אינו רשאי למשכנו. hamalveh
es haveiro eino rashai lemashkeno. Somebody who lends money to his friend
is not permitted to take a משכון, mashkon, presumably meaning by entering
into the house, as we've seen. ואינו חייב להחזיר לו. ve'eino chayav
lehachazir lo. But he—and he doesn't have to return the משכון. mashkon.
ועובר בכל השמות הללו. ve'over bechol hashemot halalu. And if he doesn't
return it, he transgresses all these prohibitions. So like, what? He's not
allowed to and he doesn't have to, but if he doesn't, he
transgresses? So the גמרא Gemara
says מאי קאמר? mai ka'amar? What is this saying? So אמר רב
ששת הכי קאמר. amar Rav Sheshet hachi ka'amar. Here's what it's saying.
המלווה את חברו אינו רשאי למשכנו. hamalveh es haveiro eino rashai lemashkeno.
You can't take a משכון, mashkon, presumably again by entering into the
house. ואם
משכנו, v'im mashkeno, if you did, either in violation or maybe with
בית דין. beis din. חייב להחזיר, chayav lehachazir, it's not אינו חייב
להחזיר, eino chayav lehachazir, the word אינו eino was a mistake. He
amends the ברייתא. braisa. You have to be מחזיר, machzir, that's the
case of the poor being מחזיר, machzir, חייב להחזיר לו chayav lehachazir
lo ועובר בכל השמות הללו ve’over bechol hashemos halalu
א סיפא, a seifa, and if you weren't מחזיר, machzir, then you
would transgress all the prohibitions. What prohibitions? רש"י Rashi lists them. He
says השב תשיב את העבוט, hashev tashiv es ha’avos, מצות עשה mitzvas
asei return it, לא תשכב בעבוטו, lo sishkav ba’avoto, don't lie down,
כבוא השמש תשיבנו לו. kevo hashemesh teshivenu lo. Okay, so different all
these mitzvos, positive and negative mitzvos of returning it. And that's going
on the last phrase. It says not אינו חייב להחזיר eino chayav
lehachazir but חייב להחזיר. chayav lehachazir. And if you didn't מחזיר, machzir,
you'll transgress all these prohibitions. רבא אמר הכי קאמר, Rava amar hachi
kamar, רבא Rava says no, here's how to read the
ברייתא. braisa. המלווה חברו אינו רשאי למשכנו, Hamaveh chavaro eino rashai lemashkono,
you're not allowed to take collateral, again presumably by entering into his
house or forcibly taking collateral like we said even in the marketplace.
ואם משכנו, ve’im mashkeno, if you did, either by transgressing or through
בית דין, beis din,
חייב להחזיר לו, chayav lehachazir lo, you have to return it.
So so far, okay, so far it's like we said before. במה
דברים אמורים, Bamei devarim amurim, but he's going to maintain the אינו
חייב eino chayav by sticking in the following phrase. במה דברים אמורים
שמשכנו שלא בשעת הלוואתו. Bamei devarim amurim shemashkeno shelo beshas halva’aso. When
is this prohibition of taking the collateral and the חיוב chiyuv to
return the collateral in force? When it comes when the guy's in
arrears, after the, like after the loan was made. אבל משכנו שלא
בשעת הלוואתו, Aval mashkeno shelo beshas halva’aso,
yes
yes, but presumably also if it's in the period when I still
don't have to pay, you don't have a right to take the
משכון mashkon either. The primary point is, you're right, there are three
times. The time of the loan, while before the loan is due,
and after the loan is due. Okay, but presumably before the loan
is due even through בית דין beis din or whatever, you don't
have the right to take. Right. So we're talking the primarily we're
talking about at the time of the loan and after it's due.
So when do all these apply? After the loan is due, that's
when there's a prohibition of entering the house and שלא בשעת הלוואתו,
shelo beshas halva’aso, when it's not the moment of the loan. After
it's due, then there's the prohibition and then you have to return
it on a daily basis. אבל משכנו בשעת הלוואתו, Aval mashkeno beshas
halva’aso, an arrangement made at the time of the loan. So that
was just part of the transaction. אינו חייב להחזיר לו, eino chayav
lehachazir lo, you don't have to return it because, right, that's not
like you as we discussed initially the whole idea of your power
and you know, you have because he owes you money, you can't
exert that power and enter into the house. Okay, at the time
of the loan we're equally empowered sides and we're making a transaction
that we have based on our arrangements. So he gives you, you
can take collateral at that time and then you don't have to
return it. Then it's not, it's not seen in the context of
that power dynamic.
Obviously, because one person needs the money and one person doesn't, but
nevertheless, it's not the same, you know, imbalance as after the money
has been lent.
I think there's a greater power disparity before the loan is made
because the poor guy needs the money now and he's got to
do whatever he has to do in order to get it. Once
he's got the money, he's got a little bit more
power over the lender.
Well, it's true he might not pay the lender, but the lender
now has a legal right against this person, right? And the lender
can take legal action against this and, you know, and he's indebted
to the lender. Even though I need the money, you could say
no and I'll go find it from somebody else. So I still,
our relationship is not written in stone at that moment when I
still need the money, right? And if I don't like this negotiation,
I'm still in power. I need it, but I can still make
choices here. I can make choices as, you know, if I don't
like what you're saying, I'll try to find somebody else. So I
hear the point, but I think that there, I think that's sort
of where the difference lies. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this, so but שלא בשעת הלוואתו, shelo beshas halva’aso, בשעת הלוואתו,
beshas halva’aso, it's all fine. אבל משכנו בשעת הלוואתו, Aval mashkeno beshas
halva’aso, אינו חייב להחזיר לו, eino chayav lehachazir lo, ועובר בכל השמות
הללו ve’over bechol hashemos halalu א רישא. a reisha. That's the first
scenario about when it was שלא בשעת הלוואתו. shelo beshas halva’aso. Okay,
so that was very important clarifying the, however you read the ברייתא,
braisa, clarifying that these issues are שלא בשעת הלוואתו. shelo beshas halva’aso.
תני רב שיזי קמיה דרבא. Tani Rav Shizi kamei deRava. רב שיזי
Rav Shizi taught in front of רבא. Rava. כבוא השמש תשיבנו לו,
Kevo hashemesh teshivenu lo, until the sun sets you should return it,
before the sun sets you should return it. So זו כסות
לילה, zu ksus lailah,
so
I'm sorry, until the sun rises you should return it. So this
means you have it at night and you return it before the
sun rises. So there's different פסוקים, psukim, one in שמות Shemos and
one in דברים. Devarim. So דברים Devarim says return it before sunrise.
זו כסות לילה, zu ksus lailah, that's a night garment. Make sure
to return it to before sunrise. So the גמרא Gemara is going
to say what good does it do the עני oni that you're
giving him his night garment at sunrise? כבוא השמש Kevo hashemesh means
sunset.
No, כבוא השמש kevo hashemesh means sunset because the sun is coming
down to the earth. I understand.
Maybe here it means something different, but the פשט pshat in the
תנ"ך Tanach as I understand it is כבוא השמש kevo hashemesh is
nighttime.
Right. כבוא השמש, Kevo hashemesh, the גמרא Gemara here is reading it,
I'm not disagreeing with you about the תנ"ך Tanach reading, but the
גמרא Gemara here is reading
it... Oh, but רש"י *Rashi* does read בוא השמש *Bo HaShemesh* like,
I'm sorry, רש"י *Rashi* does read בוא השמש *Bo HaShemesh* meaning sunset,
but he reads it ויהי בידו עד בוא השמש שייטלנו ממנו *Veyehi
beyado ad Bo HaShemesh sheyitlanu mimeno*. So you're actually correct in terms
of the meaning, right? רש"י *Rashi* does read בוא *bo* means sunset,
but it means עד *ad*, I guess is תשיבנו לו *teshivenu lo*,
let it remain with him until sunset. Okay, so thank you for
the correction. Okay. So let it remain with him until sunset, זו
כסות לילה *zo kesut layla*, the night garment let it remain with
the borrower until sunset. השב תשיב לו את העבוט כבוא השמש *Hashev
teshiv lo et ha-avot kevo hashemesh*, return it to him at sunset,
let him keep it at night, זו כסות יום *zo kesut yom*,
that's a day garment. So the way we're reading it is, one
says let him keep it during the day and one says let
him keep it at night, and we're reading it let him keep
night garments in the day and day garments at night. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says, so אמר ליה *amar lei*, so he said to,
so רב שיזבי *Rav Shizbi* said back to the person teaching this
ברייתא *braita*, דיממא דליליא למה לי ודליליא דיממא למה לי *diyamama de-leilya
lama li ve-de-leilya di-yamama lama li*? What does a guy need day
garments at night and night garments in the day? What do you
mean let the עני *ani* have the garment back during the day
means have his pajamas back during the day? What good is that
going to do him? אמר ליה *amar lei*, איסמייא *ismaya*, so should
I erase this ברייתא *braita*, is this ברייתא *braita* an error? אמר
ליה *amar lei*, לא *lo*, no. הכי קאמר *hachi ka'amar*, here's how
to read the ברייתא *braita*: עד בוא השמש תשיבנו לו *ad Bo
HaShemesh teshivenu lo*, have him have it, so again to correct the
reading from before, have it until sunset, keep it during the day,
זו כסות יום *zo kesut yom*, so the borrower keeps his day
garments during the day, שניתנה לחבול בלילה *shenitna lachavol balayla*, that's what
you have a right to hold onto during the night are day
garments. So when it called it a night garment it meant a
garment that you have the right to hold onto at night because
it's a day garment. Yes, yes, yes. Anyway, השב תשיב לו את
העבוט כבוא השמש *Hashev teshiv lo et ha'avot kevo hashemesh*, return it
to him by sunset, have him have it at night. What does
he have at night? זו כסות לילה *zo kesut layla*, give him
his night garments at night שניתנה לחבול ביום *shenitna lachavol bayom*, from
your perspective they're day garments because you hold onto them during the
day. Anyway בקיצור *bekitser*, give him back his day garments in the
day and his night garments at night. אמר רבי יוחנן *Amar Rabbi
Yochanan*, said רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, משכון mashkon ומת שומטו מעל גבי
בניו *mashkon umet shomto me-al gabei banav*, you took the משכון *mashkon*
and the guy died and let's say you had returned it, right?
I'm returning back and forth this garment every day and then the
guy died, the debtor died. I can go and take that cloak
back from the heirs. Now the חידוש *chiddush* here is that normally
you would say if somebody owes me money and he dies I
only have liens on the real estate, I don't have liens on
the chattel. But because this has been my משכון *mashkon* even though
I've been returning it on a daily basis I have rights to
it and I can take it even after the guy's dead even
though I can't take other chattel I can take this, okay? Right,
yes, ומת שומטו מעל
גבי בניו *umet shomto me-al gabei banav*. מתיבי *Mativei*, objects this. אמר
רבי מאיר *Amar Rabbi Meir*, וכי מאחר שממשכנין למה מחזירין *vechi me'achar
she-memashkenin lama machzirin*, once you take collateral why do you return it?
So the גמרא *Gemara* says, למה מחזירין *lama machzirin*? What do you
mean why do you return it? רחמנא אמר הדר *Rachmana amar hadar*,
the תורה *Torah* says to return it. So אלא *ella* no, מאחר
שמחזיר למה חוזר וממשכן *me'achar she-machzir lama chozer u-memashken*, once the תורה
*Torah* obligates me to return
it what good does it do me after I took it and
I returned it back? So why do I go the next day
to take it again? I'm just going to have to give it
back again. What good does this whole little exercise do me as
the creditor? So here's the practical benefit: שלא תהא שביעית משמטתו *she-lo
tehei shevi'it meshamtetto*, שמיטה shmita *shmita* won't annul it. Since I have
to some degree symbolically the loan is already seized and in my
possession through this משכון *mashkon*, שמיטה shmita *shmita* won't annul the loan.
ולא יהא מטלטלין אצל בניו *velo yehei metaltelin etzel banav*, and also
if the debtor dies I'll be able to collect from this and
I won't be limited to collecting from land because I've taken this
as a משכון *mashkon*. So the reason to continue this exercise of
borrowing and returning and borrowing and returning is to get those concrete
benefits. So the גמרא *Gemara* says one minute, but that טעמא דהדר
ומשכניה *ta'ama de-hadar umashkeniya*, that sounds like because you retook it it
prevents שמיטה *shmita* and it prevents it from being, and it allows
you to collect from it. But that sounds like only because you're
currently in possession of it. And but if it's actually if the
guy died at the time when it was back in his home
it sounds like maybe you wouldn't have those rights. אי לא הדר
ומשכניה *ei lo hadar umashkeniya*, if you didn't take it back yet,
if it's now in this guy's home and he dies, לא *lo*,
it sounds like you wouldn't, sounds like you need to be physically
in possession to have those rights. So אמר רב אדא בר מתנא
*amar Rav Adda bar Matna*, דלא תירצת קא מותיב ליה *dela tiratzta
ka mutiv lei*, wait you've already edited the ברייתא *braita*, תירץ הכי
*tiratz hachi*, so read it this
way: וכי מאחר שמחזירין למה ממשכנין מעיקרא *vechi me'achar she-machzirin lama memashkenin
me'ikara* and not why do you go and recollect it on a
daily basis, why do you bother with the entire exercise, why did
you bother to take collateral if you're just going to have to
return it every single day? And the answer is שלא תהא שביעית
משמטתו ולא יהא מטלטלין אצל בניו *shelo tehei shevi'it meshamtetto velo yehei
metaltelin etzel banav* because once you've taken it as collateral it won't
be annulled and you'll be able to collect. The difference of the
second reading is even if the guy dies or שמיטה arrives when
it is in his home, it doesn't matter whether you're right now
physically in possession or not physically in possession, the fact that you
took it as collateral, even though now we're going to go through
this game of back and forth and back and forth, right, provides
you with those types of benefits of rights in terms of שמיטה
and that you can collect. Now I just want to read one
little תוספות Tosfos and we'll end with that. למה משכנין מעיקרא? Lama
mashkinin meikara? It says הקשה רב חננאל, Hiksha Rav Chananel, זה למה
חוזרין ומשכנין. Zelama chozrin umashkinin. So I took it once and I
returned it. Now I have the benefits of שמיטה won't annul it
and I'll be able to collect after the guy dies. Why do
I bother the next day and the day after that and the
day after that? You think people are going to forget. ויש לומר
כדי שלא יוכל הלווה לכפור, Veyesh lomar kedei shelo yuchal haloveh lichfor,
because now I also have proof that he owes me the money
with the holding of the collateral. וגם ימהר לפרוע החוב Vegam yemarei
lifroa hachov ולבקש מעות כי יתבייש בכל יום ויום יחזירו משכונו. Ulivakesh
maos ki yitbaiesh bechol yom vayom yachziro mashkono. Even though he gets
his pajamas back at night, it's a little degrading every single day
to be going through this exercise and having this guy come and
collect the משכון and so on. So it creates, right, it's demeaning,
right, better word. So anyway, so that creates a strong incentive for
me to pay up בכל יום. bechol yom. Okay. So therefore those
are the benefits that you get, although you do have to return
it on a daily basis, you still have these very concrete benefits
and that's how the whole sort of structure works. Okay.